请勿在家尝试本片中的任何实验
Please, do not try what you are about to see at home.
我们就是你们所称的专家
We're what you call experts.
看不出来吗
Can't you tell?
本集《流言终结者》中
On this episode of "Mythbusters"...
■
本字幕由人人影视字幕组翻译
禁止用作任何商业盈利行为
翻译：小囧子  Karena酱
大家好
Hello.
我正身处被大众称为M5大楼下方
I'm talking to you from a bunker two leagues
翻译：feilixiaozi  Foxer
9.5千米处的一间地堡里
below a building known to the public as M5.
翻译：某羽  波比  噪音小子
在我身后
Behind me,
海曼正在观看数百个
the Hyneman watches hundreds of feeds
轴轴：雪贵人  小狱
《流言终结者》的历年片段
from "Mythbusters" of years past.
但这并不是自恋
But not out of narcissism.
校对：皇冠  萌Su
不  他是有目的的
No, this has a purpose.
海曼的特异能力  能让他浏览
The powers that be have allowed the Hyneman to sift through
后期：8T
这十年来测试过的所有流言
all the constructions that he's done over the past 10 years
并找出一个不满意的  重新验证
to find one that he found unsatisfying and wants to revisit,
这会让他微笑
One that will bring a smile,
那是一抹隐藏在巨大胡须下的笑容
and an invisible smile underneath his prodigious moustache.
你能闭嘴吗
Would you shut up?
是啊  闭嘴吧  亚当
Yeah, can it, Adam,
因为这一集全部是关于二次机遇
Because this episode is all about second chances.
面对十多年的剧集和八百五十条流言
With over a decade of episodes and 850 myths to choose from...
二  一
Two...One.
他们仔细筛查了存档
they've scanned the archives
寻找最大的未解流言
for their greatest, unsolved myth-teries.
当炸药和手工再次结合
Adam and Jamie have a blast from the past...
亚当和杰米再享爆炸之乐
as they mix dynamite and diy once again.
接下来还会发明什么呢
Oh, what modern inventions will we come up with next?
但他们能否...
But can they deck the walls...
我管这个叫迷幻的春天
I call this my psychedelic spring.
用爆炸粉刷房间呢
and paint a room with a boom?
恭喜  你把死星造了出来
Congratulations. You finally made the death star.
起爆
Go.
与此同时  卡莉  托里和格兰特
Meanwhile, Kari, Tory, and Grant...
它浮起来了
It floats.
分裂号2
正在努力满足粉丝的要求
are fulfilling a fan fantasy...
这一定会很棒
Oh, this is gonna be so awesome.
全速前进  将船一劈为二
going full steam ahead to split a boat...
撞裂它
Mythity split it. ...
先在海上测试
Testing first by sea...
加油  加油  加油  加油
Come on, come on, come on, come on!
再回到陆地上
and then on land.
就是它了
This is it, man.
三  二  一
Three, two, one!
但他们最终能否将木头劈断
But can they finally splinter their timbers...
让船一分为二呢
and tear a boat in two?
有一点我很喜欢
If there's one thing I like,
速度真快
it's fast.
流言终结者是何方神圣
Who are the mythbusters?
亚当·沙维奇
Adam Savage...
我拒绝你的真实性并将用我的来代替
I reject your reality and substitute my own.
以及杰米·海曼
and Jamie Hyneman.
有点太令人振奋了
It's almost too exciting.
他们有超过三十年的特技经验
Between them, more than 30 years of special-effects experience.
和他们二位一道的有格兰特·今原
Together with Grant Imahara...
这就是为什么好东西不能落入我们手中
This is why we can never have anything nice.
卡莉·拜伦
Kari Byron...
手中枪越大  科学越有趣
Science gets more fun when I get a bigger gun.
以及托里·贝鲁奇
and Tory Belleci.
跟我的小朋友打个招呼吧
Say hello to my little friend!
他们不光叙述流言
They don't just tell the myths.
他们还将流言付诸实践
They put them to the test.
流言终结者
第十二季 第九集
十周年纪念
首先  亚当和杰米要复习一下他们的杰作
First, Adam and Jamie are brushing up on their arts and blasts.
炸药涂料  第二部
在家收看的各位
For those of you playing at home,
"炸药涂料"是多年前的一集节目
"Painting with explosives" is a show we did years ago
流言基于英国喜剧《憨豆先生》中的一集
based on an episode of the British comedy "Mr. Bean"...
在剧中  一根炸药被插在了涂料桶中
in which a stick of dynamite is placed in a bucket of paint.
当炸药爆炸后
and when it blows up,
房间被完美地粉刷  并且没有损伤
It perfectly paints the room it's in without destroying the room.
对  但我们的爆炸并不是很理想
Yeah, but our explosives didn't do a very good job of it, did they?
不理想
No.
我们的结果更像是
I think we ended up more, like,
把墙弄脏了  而不是粉刷了一遍
staining the walls than actually painting them.
对  感觉就像是杰克逊·波洛克的作品
Yeah, it was a Jackson Pollack sort of a moment.
杰克逊·波洛克  以巨幅的"滴色"画而出名
可以这么说吧
Yeah. Barely.
炸药涂料S04E09
上一次我们测试这个大规模装潢武器时
The last time we tested this weapon of mass decoration...
一
One.
我们的粉刷器和雷管
our painters and detonators...
覆盖面  非常小
Coverage -- total crap.
将涂料喷到了墙上
got paint on the walls...
真是糟透了
That's horrible.
但那并不能叫做装修
but you wouldn't call it home improvement.
那么  你认为这次可以做得到吗
So, you think you can actually do it this time?
你有什么新计划吗
You have a new design in mind?
我愿意试一下
Well, I'd like to try.
而且如你所知
And as you know,
我可以控制爆炸中释放的能量
I have a thing about actually harnessing the power of explosives
让其做功  而不是把一切炸得乱七八糟
to do work instead of just blowing crap up.
我也有一些自己的想法
I have some ideas of my own.
要不这样  这一集里
Let's say, for this episode,
我们分头尝试自己的办法
we go off to our separate corners and each try a solution
看看能否达到用爆炸粉刷墙壁的目的
and see if we can't finally achieve painting with explosives.
-听起来不错  -好的
- Sounds like fun.   - All right.
那么  他们即将分头工作
So, the guys will split up,
每人制造一个自己的涂料炸弹
and each craft their own room boom.
不过先要到爆炸实验场去研究一番
But that's going to take some bomb-range R and D.
多美好的一天啊
What a lovely day.
我们来炸点什么东西吧
Let's blow something up.
第一位拾起"画笔"的是亚当
And first to take up the brush is Adam.
我要从零开始
I'm going all the way back to basics.
我要用一小块C4炸药
I'm gonna take a little chunk of C-4
一包涂料还有一个平面
and a bag of paint and a surface,
然后引爆C4
And I'm gonna blow up the C-4
看看涂料会怎样分散到平面上
And watch what it does to the paint on the surface.
亚当的计划是从小做起
So, Adam's plan is to start small...
C4放在这里
C-4 goes here.
涂料挂在这里
Paint hangs here.
我的测试画布立在这里
My test canvas goes here.
在J.D.纳尔逊的监督下
Under the watchful eye of J.D. Nelson
测试涂料炸到画布上会怎样分散开
to explore what happens when paint meets explosive meets canvas.
炸药涂料
Painting with explosives.
第一次测试  三  二  一  起爆
First experiment in three, two, one, go.
有意思  真有意思
Fascinating. Fascinating.
就那样掉下去了
It just, like, goes,
这跟我想象的可不一样
That's not at all what I expected to happen.
这就是实验信息
That's information.
这就是这整个测试的目的所在
That was the whole point of this test.
覆盖面积比亚当需要的少得多
That fraction of coverage is a long way from what Adam needs...
镜头回放阐明了原因
And the action replay reveals why.
涂料还在那里
The paint's still there.
完全没有蒸发
It's totally not vaporizing.
离得太远了
Its' too far away.
这就是根本原因
That is radical.
棒极了
Awesome. Okay.
我知道接下来该怎么做了
I know what to do next.
第二次测试  亚当做了些调整
Yep. For test two, Adam's got something different on his plate.
这次爆破和上次的不同点在于
So, the difference between this blast and the last one
我将会把涂料移得更近
Is that I am going to move the paint much closer --
就在C4的正上方
In fact, right on top of the C-4 --
其次  也许你已经看懂了
And second, as you probably already surmised by this,
我将会给C4加一个反射板
I'm going to give the C-4 a reflecting backing plate,
这块又大又结实的钢板
This big, heavy piece of steel.
太好了  炸药来了
Oh, cool. There it is.
给你
There you go.
我不确定这招是否可行
I'm not actually sure if this is gonna work,
但这次效果会和上次大不一样
but it's gonna be really different than the last one,
应该能给我一些信息
and that's gonna tell me something.
倒数三  二  一  爆
In three, two, one, go.
这个更有效果
That was far more effective.
反射板的确把涂料反弹到了画布上
The backing plate certainly reflected the paint onto the board
还喷得到处都是
and everywhere else.
看看
There we go.
你好
Hi, there.
你怎么样
How you doing?
你好
Hi.
蓝涂料爆炸的慢镜头回放
The high-speed shot of my blue-paint explosion
真的非常棒
is absolutely gorgeous.
产生了我想看到的涂料雾
I got exactly the vaporized fog of paint that I was looking for,
并且几乎都喷到了用来接收涂料的
and most of it ended up on the four-by-eight of wood
1.2米乘2.4米木板上
that I had placed there to receive the paint.
这和把涂料
It's about as far as you'd get
粉刷到板上去基本上差不多
if you wanted to roll that much paint onto that board.
涂料覆盖度正是亚当想要的
And that's exactly the kind of coverage Adam was looking for.
但他觉得还有提升空间
But he still thinks he can improve on it.
这次实验中  我会用这个
In this test, I'll be using this.
这是个很薄的增塑片状炸药
It's actually a thin sheet of plasticized, sheet explosive,
就像一片C4炸药牛肉干一样
sort of a C4 jerky, if you will.
不过别吃啊
But don't eat it!
我要用它来涂涂料
No. I'm gonna paint with it.
把炸药分散到涂料下方
But will spreading the explosive under the paint
会不会扩大涂料的覆盖范围呢
also spread the coverage?
来吧
All right, here we go.
最后一次爆炸  三  二  一  爆
Final explosion in three, two, one, go.
威力比我想象中大
That was more powerful than I expected it to be.
威力有点太大了
That was a little too much oomph.
我们去看看涂得怎样
Well, let's go see how it did with the painting anyway.
与其说是稍微粉刷  不如说是墙上泼墨
It was less a lick of paint and more a riot of color.
这个在这里
That goes there.
看到拼凑好的画布后  亚当受到了启发
But piecing back together his canvas has inspired Adam.
我觉得今天是很有成就的一天
Well, for me, that was a very successful and excellent day,
不仅仅因为炸了一天的东西
and not just because I spent the day blowing stuff up.
更因为在爆破的过程中
Because in blowing stuff up, I actually learned --
我了解了所有与炸药涂料
I believe I learned everything I need to know
有关的信息
to paint with explosives,
包括用多少炸药算过量
including how much explosives is too much.
要开工啦
Time to get to work.
亚当启程返回工作室
So, Adam heads back to the shop,
另一位流言终结者在车间倒腾喷嘴
where another mythbuster has been playing with his nozzles.
我是这么想的
The way I see it,
如果能用一个喷嘴把一次爆炸的涂料
if I can get a single blast of paint going through a nozzle
均匀地喷到一面墙上
to cover an entire wall perfectly evenly,
那我用几个喷嘴同时涂几面墙
Then if I have multiple nozzles painting multiple walls,
就能用一次爆炸  粉刷整个房间
I can get a single blast of paint to paint a whole room.
我认为这种扁平的孔
I'm thinking that this sort of flattened orifice here
能限制涂料
is restricting the paint
让其不以圆锥状
to where it doesn't come out in a cone,
而是以矩状喷出
but rather, it comes out in a rectangle.
这正是我想要的
And that's exactly what I need.
正是他想要的
It's exactly what he needs.
但还有很多工作需要做
But a hose is a long way from an explosion.
有这个想法后
With that in mind,
我拿出了以前做的这个装置
I've broken out this rig that I built some time ago,
因为里面的压强可到约4800千帕
because it'll allow me to test with up to about 700 psi,
看看涂料能不能更加发散
and we'll see if that fans it out more.
杰米想要让涂料呈矩状喷向墙壁
Jamie's aiming for a rectangular spread onto the wall.
开太大了
Too far open.
但想要喷得刚刚好  需要精细调整
But it's a delicate business of tweaking his nozzle just so...
我觉得第一次更好
I liked the first one better.
最后  他终于找到了合适的比例
Until eventually, he finds his goldilocks ratio.
三  二  一
Three, two, one.
看起来挺好的
It's looking pretty good.
拿着他的喷嘴
Yep, and with his nozzle in hand,
杰米来到爆炸实验场
Jamie heads to the bomb range...
来检测理论的第二部分
to put part two of this theory to the test.
像石头一样坚固
Solid as a rock.
我的想法是
My theory is that this time around,
这次需要把涂料和炸药
we need to contain the paint and the explosives
放进像这样的高压氧气罐里
in something like this high-pressure, scuba tank.
当爆炸发生时
And when the explosives go off,
涂料会从氧气罐中通过喷嘴喷出
the paint will be propelled out the nozzle of the tank
就像一个喷雾嘴一样
kind of like a spray nozzle.
我们就能看到一面涂好的墙了
And we'll end up with our nicely painted wall.
希望不会变成一个铁管炸弹
Hopefully not a pipe bomb.
杰米的方法  关键就在于压力
Yep. Jamie's method all comes down to pressure.
但首先
But first,
将炸药放进一罐涂料里会发生什么呢
what happens when you put explosives inside a tank of paint?
第一次实验  C4炸药  无喷嘴
All right. This is test one, C4, no nozzle,
三  二 一  爆
in three, two, one, go.
还挺不错的
That -- that actually is quite nice.
看上去大部分涂料都喷出来了
It looked like it sent most of the paint out.
没炸开
No rupture.
确实没有炸开
It didn't blow,
所以第二罐不仅装了涂料
So tank two is filled with paint,
还装上了海曼调节的喷嘴
and then fitted with the patented, hyneman nozzle.
但矩形喷嘴加上加压涂料
But will the combo of rectangular nozzle
真的能粉刷一面墙吗
and pressurized paint cover the wall?
三  二  一
In three, two, one.
好吧
Well.
氧气筒还是没炸开
Once again, the tank survived,
但喷嘴看上去
But the nozzle doesn't seem
对涂料覆盖面也没起到作用
to have made any difference to the coverage.
氧气罐基本上已经达到极限了
We're pushing the limits with what we can get with these tanks,
但覆盖面积没有到达我想要的效果
and the fact is that I'm not creating the kind of spread that I need.
我需要加大压力才行
I need more pressure to get that spread.
所以要回去再想点子了
So, I think it's back to the drawing board.
下节  流言终结者
Later, can the mythbusters
能用大爆炸绘制高雅艺术吗
make high art with high explosives?
爆
Go.
我的天啊
My gosh.
卡莉  托里和格兰特在水上起航
And Kari, Tory, and Grant weigh anchor on water.
分裂号2代
流言分裂
Mythity split it.
但"劈船为二"的诅咒会重现吗
But will the curse of the bifurcated boat return?
流言终结者十多年来一直在测试  证实
The mythbusters have been testing, confirming,
和终结流言
and busting for over 10 years.
现在他们要搞定一些未解之流言
And now they're closing the case on some unsolved myth-teries.
劈船为二
如果你们不记得这个故事  来回顾一下
Now, if you guys don't remember the story, it goes like this.
一个人开的快艇失控了
A man is driving his speedboat out of control
撞向航标杆
and crashes into a channel marker,
差点把快艇一分为二
almost splitting the boat in half.
航道标志穿过快艇
他告诉保险公司
Now, he tells the insurance company
他的行驶速度仅为40公里每小时
that he was only traveling at 25 miles an hour.
事故原因是因为驾驶者被一艘帆船的灯光刺到双眼
快艇的速度是40公里每小时
我们做过实验  根本不能分裂快艇
When we tried it, we couldn't split the boat.
我的速度只是每小时40公里
连裂口都撞不出来
We couldn't even get a tear.
我们的实验结果一点都不壮观
Yeah, our results were less than spectacular.
但根据粉丝回复
But according to you fans,
这是因为我们的方法完全是错的
that's because our methodology was totally wrong.
因为我们没在水上完成实验
Because we didn't do it on water.
没错  所以此时此刻我们要重新做实验
Exactly. So, right here, right now, we are gonna retest it.
我们要做到一石二鸟
We're gonna kill two birds with one stone.
劈船为二S05E08
他们说这是受诅咒的流言
It was the myth they said was cursed.
但除了下大雨
But despite the rain...
我都已经不求啥结果了
I'm pretty much over this one.
各种问题
the problems...
我们的缆绳是不是松了
Did we lose the cable?
还有争论
the arguments...
兄弟  我们从来不用蓝绳子的
Dude, we never use the blue rope.
-我们一直都用蓝绳子的  -才不是
- We always use the blue rope!   - No, we haven't.
还有事故
And the accidents...
他们没能把船劈成两半
The guys could never split the boat.
时速四十公里这流言不成立
The story's busted at 25.
但观众们认为 只在陆地上实验
However, the fans say this land-loving test...
简直是瞎搞
was a flub.
十周年纪念第二集  啥计划
All right. 10-year take 2. What's the plan?
很明显
Well, it's obvious.
我们要遵从观众的意见在水上实验
We have to test this on water just like the fans asked.
我们需要一艘船和一个航标杆
Well, we need a boat and a channel marker,
但要如何让它们相撞
But how do we get the two to crash?
按我们之前的做法不就行了
Why don't we do it the same way?
这次我们用摩托艇
This time, we just use powerboats.
说得简单
You make it sound so easy.
我们可比当年成熟聪明多了
Now we're older and wiser.
我们的确老了
We are older.
尽管还是相同的流言
Yep. Although the myth is the same --
让一艘快艇以四十公里的时速撞上航标杆
crash a speedboat at 25 miles an hour into a channel marker --
但这次他们不在陆地上实验
Instead of testing on the runway,
而是把船放进了湖里
they'll float their boat on a lake.
取代一辆拖车的是
And rather than using a tow truck,
两艘拖船
they'll use a pair of towboats.
为了进行水上实验
So, to weigh anchor on water...
他们来到了位于奥克利的大破码头
It's off to Big Break marina in Oakley.
船在那儿
So, that's the boat.
太棒了
Oh, that is awesome.
就是它
There she is.
让我想起了往事
That brings back memories --
虽然不全都是好事
and not all of them good.
记住  我们要把船撞到航标杆上去
Now, remember, we have to crash our boat into a channel marker.
可以看到  这个小码头到处都是航标杆
Now, as you can see, this marina is filled with them.
但是  码头工作人员
But for some reason,
可不想让我们的船撞上去
they don't want us to crash our boat into theirs.
所以我们需要自己立一根
So, we need to plant our own.
这可不是个简单的活
Now, this is no easy job.
那可是根十二米高的木杆
I mean, we're talking about a 40-foot pole
要将它插入近四米深的地下
being sunk 12 feet into the ground
还是在水上完成
while on top of the water.
幸运的是  我们的朋友  罗布
And luckily for us, Rob, our friend here,
有一架悬浮打桩机
has a floating pile driver.
没错
Indeed.
在罗布将木桩插入指定区域后
And with Rob driving our pole into the delta...
成败就在此一举了
It's time to shape up and ship out.
分裂号
二代
我们像上次一样卸掉了发动机
We've removed the engine just like last time,
我们用与发动机等质量的水
So we're going to replace the equivalent weight of the engine
代替发动机的重量
with barrels full of water.
水桶都放好之后  是时候下水一试了
And with the barrels aboard, it's time to hit the waves.
看看有没有漏水的地方
Check for holes.
第一步
Step one,
它浮起来了
it floats.
成功浮起
It floats.
现在为船加上发动机的重量
And now to give it the equivalent ballast of an engine.
但要让它在水中动起来
But to get it moving on water,
需要点儿外界帮助
It's gonna need help.
这就是我们的拖船
These are our towboats.
你没听错  两艘船
That's right. You heard me. Two boats.
因为水的阻力太大  一艘船拉不动
because there's too much water resistance for just one.
每艘拖船配备了一台175马力的发动机
Each of these boats has a 175-horsepower engine.
这应该有足够的拉力
That should be plenty of power
让我们的快艇达到时速四十公里
to get our speedboat up to 25 miles an hour.
时速四十公里的快艇
Up to 25 miles per hour...
撞上崭新的航标杆
and into the newly installed, picture-perfect channel marker.
在装配好实验最重要的部分之前
Before we rig all the important components to this experiment,
我觉得我们需要点儿真实感
I thought we needed a little authenticity
让它看起来像流传的照片那样
and make this look just like the viral photo.
拖船已经准备好  随时可以开始实验
And with the tow system working, they're ready to test.
分裂号2代
但正当设置摄像机时
But while the cameras reset...
分裂号2
什么
What the...
不
Oh, no!
悲剧发生了
Tragedy strikes.
你可能很想知道
You're probably wondering why
为什么会有一艘大型驳船行驶在我们的航道上
there's a giant barge in the middle of our channel,
我们也在考虑同一个问题
and we were wondering the same thing.
接下来
And then, that
驳船离我们的航标杆越来越近
barge got closer and closer to our channel marker,
最后把它撞进了水里
and it actually knocked it over into the water.
现在  我们的工作人员正在寻找它
In fact, our crew, right now, is looking for it,
并试图打捞上来
trying to fish it out.
你们找到了吗
Did you guys find it yet?
还没
Not yet.
太有"流言终结者"风格了
This is so "Mythbusters."
当所有事都按部就班进行的时候
I mean, everything was going so smoothly.
肯定会出点儿问题
Something had to go wrong.
但与航标杆不同  流言仍在那里等待验证
But unlike the marker, this myth ain't sunk yet.
粉刷工作真的能像
Could painting be as easy as
"三  二  一  嘭"那么简单吗
"Three, two, one, boom"?
炸药涂料S04E09
流言终结者们上次尝试的时候
Well, when the mythbusters tried this,
他们用炸药粉刷失败了
Their TNT DIY was D.O.A.
我还指望会比这好点儿
I thought it would be a little better than that.
现在  增加了七年的爆炸经验
Now, armed with seven years' more explosives experience,
他们的第一步是掌握炸药涂料的基本原理
Their first stop was painting and detonation 101.
这都是信息
That's information.
我们做这个实验就是为了获得这个
That was the whole point of this test.
M5工业有限公司
回到工作室
And back at the shop,
杰米可是对这项研究"满罐"干劲
Jamie's "Tankful" for all that research.
看到这个罐子差一点被炸开
Having seen this tank darn near rupture from an explosion
我们发现在爆炸的时候
points out the fact that when an explosive goes off,
炸药的能量
the energy from it
会向四周均匀的发散
wants to travel outward evenly in all directions.
就像一个膨胀的球体
It's almost a spherical swelling.
所以
So, you know,
圆柱形的罐子可能并不适合这个实验
maybe a cylindrical tank isn't the way to go.
我们需要的可能是个球型的罐子
Maybe we need a spherical tank.
但问题是
But the problem is
你没办法像买氧气瓶一样走进商店
that you can't just go to the store and buy one
买到一个球型的罐子
like you can a scuba tank.
只能自己制作  那可不是容易的事
You got to make your own, and that's not a simple task.
虽说不容易
Not a simple task,
但海曼总能想出方法来
but the Hyneman mind will find a way.
事实上  他好像已经有主意了
In fact, it looks like he already has.
杰米想到了一个巧妙的
Jamie's thought up an ingenious,
平面方案来制作球型罐
flat-pack design for his spherical tank.
这就是我的设计
There we go.
24个2.5厘米厚的钢圈
24 one-inch-thick washers
用26个不同种类的连接件组装在一起
and 26 assorted other parts to bolt it all together.
估计重量在1.5吨左右
Looks like it ought to weigh around 3,500 pounds.
那可是个又大又沉的球
That's a big, heavy sphere.
是啊  那可不是月球
Yep. That's no moon.
出自《星球大战》
-天行者: 月球吗  -欧比旺: 那可不是月球  是宇宙飞船
将所有的钢圈切割出来
So, it's off to get those washers plasma cut
并组装到一起
and then put it all together.
这些部件组装到一起之后  它能承受
So, when this is all assembled, it should hold
最大约34.5万千帕的爆炸压力
upwards of 50,000 P.S.I. from the blast.
至少  理论上是这样的
At least, that's the plan.
虽说理论上是这样  但五十多个部分
That's the plan, but with over 50 parts
都从这样一块2.5厘米厚的钢板上切割
All cut from one-inch, heavy-duty plate...
这东西可真大
This thing's a beast.
组成了一个巨大的三维拼图
That's one giant, 3-d puzzle.
但作为他自己设计出来的难题
But as it's a brainteaser of his own design,
这可难不住杰米
Jamie has this riddle wrapped in an enigma all figured out.
这个球被做成了两半
The sphere's being made in two halves,
每半都是由
And each half is basically
一堆不同尺寸的钢圈
a stack of different-sized washers
互相堆积  焊接在一起
that get put on top of each other and welded together.
现在  洞的部分
Now, the holes leave
在球内形成一个直径25厘米的腔
a 10-inch-diameter cavity in the middle of this sphere,
涂料和炸药就会储存在那里
and that's where the paint and the dynamite goes.
好了
There we go.
当爆炸发生以后
Now, when the explosive goes off,
涂料都得向某个方向流动
all of that paint has got to go somewhere,
所以  我希望它能进入漏斗
and so, i'm hoping that it'll go right into these sort of funnel shapes
通过喷嘴喷到墙上
in these nozzles and straight out and paint our walls.
它能否粉刷整个房间呢
What it actually will do as far as painting a house,
我不太确定
I'm not really sure,
但至少我很开心
but I'm having a ball.
懂了吗  他有个球哎[玩得开心]
Get it? He's having a ball.
随着他工作到深夜
And as he works long into the night,
显然杰米的球有了浓浓的反派范
it's clear Jamie's sphere has turned to the dark side.
背景音乐和音效来自《星球大战之新希望》中
"死星"背景音乐和黑勋爵呼吸声
如果想要承受高爆
You know, if you want to contain a high explosive,
那就得这么做
that's what you got to do.
美极了
That's pretty.
当杰米在铲车后面
Well, while Jamie's working on whatever
制造他那死亡之花的时候
flower of death he's building back there behind the forklift,
我认真思考了
I have been thinking seriously
在爆炸实验场进行的实验
about the explosions that I got out on the bomb range.
言归正传
Oh. Right.
它们给了我所需的灵感
So, they have given me the ideas that I need.
所需的钢材已经切割完了
I've got all the steel cut.
我将要在工作室里
I'm about to start constructing
建造我的粉刷设备
my painting device here in the shop.
和海曼的一样  亚当的设备也不简单
Yep. And just like the Hyneman, Adam's device ain't simple.
这个粉刷设备会有很多移动部件
There's a lot of moving parts to this painting rig,
但是肯定会很酷的
but it's gonna be cool.
亚当焊了一些框架
Adam welds some frames,
然后
And then --
好吧  我们也不知道他要干什么
well, we're not quite sure what he's doing.
看似不错
Coming along.
他就希望达到这个效果
And that's exactly how he wants it to stay.
好的
All right.
现在  来猜猜看我的粉刷机
At this point, I'd like you to take a moment and speculate
是如何工作的
on how you think my painting machine works.
你知道什么很酷吗
'cause you know what's cool?
你肯定都猜错了
You're totally wrong.
这一次我没按常规出牌
I'm going way off the reservation on this one.
接下来还会发明什么呢
What modern inventions will we come up with next?
亚当的秘密设备已完成
So, with Adam's secret device apparently complete
杰米也将巨大死星装入卡车后箱
and Jamie's giant death sphere on the back of the truck,
墙壁战争可以打响了
The war on walls can begin.
三  二  一  爆
Three, two, one, go.
在大破码头
At the big break marina...
怎么回事...
What the...
一艘大驳船坏了好事
there's been a big barge break.
看起来"劈船为二"的诅咒又出现了
And it seems as though the bifurcated-boat curse is back.
又是分裂快艇这档子事
Good, old, bifurcated boat.
按照分裂号的光荣传统
In the great tradition of the mythity split,
这完全是一个被诅咒的实验
this is a completely cursed experiment.
驳船把我们的航标杆弄没了
We lost our channel marker to that barge.
不过还好我们还有另一个
But luckily, we've procured another.
坏消息是我们缺少了一些真实性
The bad news is we do lose a little authenticity
因为我们的海鸥和标牌都沉到湖底去了
as our seagull and our sign are at the bottom of the lake.
继续  托里  再往后一点
Go ahead, Tory. Back it in.
有了十年的经验
Yep, with 10 years of experience,
组员们当然知道如何拯救一个流言
our crew certainly knows how to salvage a myth.
因为他们思维敏捷  足智多谋
And thanks to their quick thinking and resourcefulness...
我觉得我们干过这个了
I feel like we've done this before.
因为确实干过了
'Cause you have.
二号木桩准备完毕
pole two is good to go.
现在粉丝们即将看到水上的测试了
And now that the fans are getting their watery way,
与之前的结果到底会有多少不同呢
just how much difference will testing in the drink make?
为什么非要用水呢
So, what's the big deal with water?
下面就是这次水上实验
Well, here's why it might make a difference
结果可能不同的原因
doing it on water this time.
因为船浮在水上
The boat is sitting on the water.
而水是不可压缩的
Water is incompressible.
这就说明船体会受到压力
That means that there's pressure on the hull.
水压
而额外的压力可能会导致
That extra pressure might translate
船首受到更大的冲击
into more impact force on the bow,
船首部位
增加了它被劈开的可能
potentially allowing it to split.
水压
第二个原因是龙骨处于水下
Second reason is that the keel is now in water,
龙骨:提供更大的稳定性
和方向控制
这有益于让船直行
helping to keep the boat straight,
也避免了船与桩仅是擦过的可能
so you avoid possibly getting a glancing blow.
为什么结果可能会没有差别呢
Now, why might it not make a difference?
想想看
Well, think about it.
船的重量是一样的
The weight of the boat is the same.
速度也是一样的
The speed is gonna be the same.
因此  撞击木桩时船体的
Therefore, we're gonna have the same amount
动能也是一样的
of kinetic energy hitting that pole.
若问我觉得结果如何
What do I think is gonna happen?
我觉得不会看到船被劈开
I don't think we're gonna get a split,
至少在四十公里的时速下不行
at least not at 25.
格兰特不抱希望
Grant's skeptical,
但经历了倒霉的上午后
but after their cursed morning,
托里只希望能顺利进行实验
Tory is hoping they can actually push the boat out.
现在你们脑子里
All right, there should be one word
应该只想着一个词了
going through your guys' heads right now,
那就是  "分裂"
And that's "Bifurcation."
但是水上实验能否让船分裂呢
But will testing this myth afloat split the boat?
好的  船已就位
All right. The boat's in place.
航标杆也立好了
Channel marker's up.
这是劈船为二  第二次
This is bifurcated boat, take two.
把它劈开
Mythity split it.
三  二  一  开始
In three, two, one, hit it.
拖船开始加速
The towboats accelerate...
分裂号起航了
And the mythity split takes off...
船动了
There's the boat.
绳索拉紧了
Oh, the rope's tensioning!
船出发了  要撞上了
Boat's away. Oh, here it comes!
缓慢加速
slowly speeding up
到流言所述的四十公里每小时
to the mythical 25 miles per hour.
船来啦
Here comes the boater!
太疯狂了  幽灵船
That looks so crazy. Ghost boat!
美极了
Oh, it's beautiful.
但是航标杆能否完成致命一击
But will the channel marker finally make its mark?
加油  加油
Come on, come on, come on, come on!
加油
Come on!
要撞上了  船头正朝向木桩
Here it comes! Headed straight for the pier.
怎么回事
What the heck?!
我们把木桩撞断了
We just took the pillar down!
被劈成两半的不该是它呀
That was the wrong thing to split.
航标杆成了两截
The marker just got split.
还真没料到这个结果
I didn't see that one coming.
我也没有
I didn't, either.
我也没想到会这样
I didn't see that coming, either.
流言里面可不是这么说的
That's not how it happened in the myth.
实验很成功  正好撞在船首上
That's a good shot, though. It hit it right on the bow.
但却没有把船劈成两半
It did not split the boat in half.
这才是最重要的事情
That is the most important thing.
这才是重要的
That's the important thing.
因为在此次惊人的撞击中
Important because in that shocking, split-second impact,
结果完全反了过来
the tables on this myth turned.
航标杆分裂了
The marker bifurcated,
而分裂号
And the mythity split refused
再次名不副实
to live up to its name once again.
我们重新实验是因为
So, the whole reason for this revisit
粉丝们都说我们之前
is that fans said that without water,
没有在水上进行实验是无效的
our original tests were invalid.
知道吗  他们是对的
You know what? They were right.
水的阻力使船
See, the resistance of the water kept the boat
直接撞了上去而不是滑开
going straight on impact without glancing off.
然而  撞击的能量
However, the energy of the impact
没有将船劈开  而是折断了杆子
caused the pole to break and not the boat.
最终  结果还是一样
So ultimately, it's the same result --
这是个被终结的流言
a busted myth.
只是得出结论的途径不同罢了
Just a slightly different way of getting there.
人们说
Now, they say
船主一生最开心的日子
that two of the happiest days of a boat owner's life
是买船和卖船的两天
is the day he buys the boat and the day he sells it.
但除非我们把船劈两半  我是不会开心
But I won't be happy until we cut that boat in half.
对  不到分裂号劈开
-Yep. It ain't over until the Mythity Split...
分裂号2代
这事没完
splits.
一
One.
你能用炸药粉刷房间吗
Can you paint a room with a boom?
在反复实验之后...
Well, after a little trial and error...
看来还得再改改我的喷嘴
Looks like I need a little bit more work on my nozzle.
每个终结者都想出了待验证的方案
each of the mythbusters have come up with a plan to find out.
在爆炸实验场
Down at the range,
是时候检验一下他们的作品了
it's time to test the state of their art.
我不知道亚当做了什么
I don't know what Adam's been up to,
但我可是忙着做我的涂料炸弹
but I've had my hands full building my paint bomb,
于是没时间建要刷的房子了
and I didn't have time to build a room to paint.
所以我们叫来一组木匠
So, we brought in a team of carpenters,
他们建了这个
and they put this
2.4米高  面积13平方米的屋子
8-foot-high-by-12-foot-square room together
来作我们的画布
as our blank canvas.
画布已经就位
The canvas is primed.
我们开工了
Here we go.
奇怪的是
But strangely,
亚当没把他的装置运到屋子附近
Adam's not unloading his device anywhere near it.
请让我为各位介绍"雪花"
Allow me to introduce the Snowflake,
我的喷涂机
my painting machine.
名字是根据
It is named after both
它的六角形状和功能而来
its hexagonal design and its uniqueness.
它的设计也参考了我之前
And its design is informed by exactly what I learned
在爆炸实验场得出的结论
out here on the bomb range earlier this week.
这就是成果
And this is the result.
有人也许会觉得
Some might feel like
我做的这个设计没有遵守规则
I have broken the rules with this design.
很明显  亚当已经谋划好了什么
Clearly, Adam's up to something.
-好了  -很好
- All right. - Good.
当他把最后一部分焊到了"雪花"上
And as he welds the final touches to the Snowflake,
杰米被弄晕了
Jamie's confused.
我猜涂料要装在中间
I'm guessing the paint goes in the middle.
没错  跟炸药放在一起
Yep, right along with the explosives.
那这些东西就在喷射的路径上
So these things are in the way.
怎么  它们是用来分散涂料还是怎么
What? Are they supposed to disperse the paint or something?
不是
Nope.
我就想把涂料喷到这些板子上
These panels are exactly where I want them to be.
那你怎么粉刷房子呢
Well, how are you gonna paint the house?
我不粉刷房子
I'm not gonna paint the house.
我要作画  装饰房子
I'm going to paint art that goes in the house.
明白了
Oh.
用爆炸"作画"
"Paintings" with explosives.
完全正确
Yeah.
作弊的不应该是我吗
I thought I'm the one that's supposed to cheat.
这次我要偷你的风头
Yeah, I thought I'd steal your thunder this time.
一般都是卑鄙的海曼
Usually, it's the underhanded Hyneman
苏打杯杀手流言
打败高速摄影机流言
决定对规矩进行变通
who decides to bend the rules...
漂浮装置流言
随意提高成功几率的
and stack the odds in his favor.
桌布混乱流言
龙卷特刊流言
-十年后...  -那块给你
- But after 10 years... - And that's for you.
显然  所有走旁门的小设计
clearly, all that devious designing
都让亚当学会了
has rubbed off on Adam.
一切始于我来到爆炸实验场
Well, this all started when I was out here at the bomb range
进行爆炸测试和喷涂的过程中
Doing my preliminary tests with painting and explosives.
我真的  真的很喜欢
I really, really liked the patterns
在目标板上出现的图案
that I was getting on my target board.
然后我就想  弄点艺术品出来如何
And I thought, "What if we made art?"
我依然是在用爆炸"喷涂"啊
I'm still technically "Painting" with explosives.
我知道杰米会全力以赴
I just figured Jamie was gonna go whole hog
把那屋子涂出来
on getting that room covered with paint,
我就可以做我想做的了
and I could kind of do my own thing.
于是我就那么干了
And that's what I did.
现在  "雪花"要进行首秀
Now it's time for the Snowflake to make its kinetic art debut
用6颗C4炸药和涂料来制作艺术品了
with six marbles of c-4 and some paint.
我管这个叫迷幻的春天
I call this My Psychedelic Spring.
我准备好了  去安全地带吧
I'm ready to go. Let's get to safety.
好了
All right.
准备好了吗  长官
You ready, sir?
-好了  -好的  我们开始
- I'm ready. - All right. Here we go.
爆炸作画
Painting with explosives
艺术创作  三  二  一
to make some art in three, two, one.
好快啊
Wow, that was quick.
确实很快
It was quick.
但把爆炸放慢到每秒1000帧时...
But when you slow the explosion to 1,000 frames per second...
太不可思议了
Wow. That is insane.
它还很漂亮
It's also beautiful.
它本身就是一件艺术品了
That's a piece of art in and of itself.
看  就像小丑的脑袋爆炸了
Look! It's like a clown's head exploded.
那是我这辈子见过
That is the loveliest thing
最可爱的东西
I have ever seen.
可炸出来的色彩  创造出了流行艺术吗
But did that explosive pop of color create pop art?
很漂亮啊
That's beautiful!
好的  一块
All right. There's one.
这张很美
Oh. Oh, it's gorgeous!
很好看
That's beautiful.
爆炸的余波发泄到画板上了
The tale of destruction wreaked on the canvas.
当亚当吹嘘着他的画...
As Adam canvasses his canvases...
真棒
Oh, yeah.
真的很好
That's really nice.
六块板确实都被涂料覆盖了
It's clear that all six were mostly covered with paint.
我不太懂艺术品
Well, I don't know much about art,
但我知道我喜欢用爆炸制造艺术品
but I know I like making it with explosives.
其中有两张颜色不错
Hey, well, two of them have some nice colors going.
还是有点潜质的
They show some promise.
也许...你可以去上上艺术课什么的
Maybe -- maybe you could take an art class or something.
你觉得呢
What do you think?
我很高兴  非常高兴
I'm very pleased. I'm very pleased.
虽然亚当的装饰艺术
But while the results
有点脏脏的
of Adam's art deco are a little muddy,
但是制作过程  漂亮至极
it's the process that was beautiful.
很好  我等不及要看杰米做了什么
Nice. Can't wait to see what Jamie comes up with.
有本事把我比下去  海曼
Top that, Hyneman.
下面  火箭滑车
Next, will a rocket sled
能完成这未解之流言吗
close the case on this unsolved myth-tery?
就是它  各位
This is it, man.
希望我们这次能把船劈成两半
Hopefully, we can cut this boat in half.
而杰米的涂料球能粉刷墙壁吗
And can Jamie's paint ball deck the wall?
我还是到观测室里面看吧
I'd like to watch this one from the bunker.
请勿在家尝试本片中的任何实验
Do not try what you are about to see at home.
我们就是你们所谓的专家
We're what you call experts.
火箭滑车轨道
Rocket-sled track.
你们准备好了吗
You guys ready for this?
要说我喜欢什么  那就是速度快
If there's one thing I like, it's fast.
动手吧
Let's do it.
超级大碰撞 2
当我们想用高速移动的墙面碾压汽车时
When we want to fly a wall down a track and pulverize a car,
当我们想在每小时643公里速度下
when we want to cause
二元炸药之汽车追尾引爆
制造一次追尾事故时
a rear-end collision at nearly 400 miles an hour...
这是我见过最酷的事
That was one of the coolest things I've ever seen!
我们都会来这里
we come here
因为第一  这里没有人  不会有危险
Because, "A," there's no one around to get in harm's way,
第二  没有人像
and, "B," Nobody does extreme
新墨西哥州工学院这帮人做得这么极端
like our friends at New Mexico Tech.
今天也不会有例外
And today is gonna be no exception.
为什么要做到这么极致
So, why are we taking it to these extremes
还要用上火箭驱动滑道呢
and using a rocket-powered sled?
因为我们按原先的速度验证流言
Well, we tested the myth just like it stated,
以每小时40公里的速度冲击航标杆
crashing a boat at 25 miles an hour into a channel marker,
但我们没法将船劈成两半
but we couldn't get it to split in half.
流言被终结了
So, the myth is busted.
现在来到我最喜欢的环节
But now it's my favorite part of the show,
流言重现
where we replicate the results.
若值得一试  就要做到最过
Now, if it's worth doing, it's worth overdoing,
这次是真的是够极致了
and I would have to say this is overdoing.
我们将用到这艘船
Now, this is the boat that we're going to use.
和流言中的船略有不同
It's not the exact same boat as the one in the myth,
但没关系
but it's gonna do just fine.
质量会相同
It will be weighted the same.
它们的制作材料相同
It's made of the same materials.
而且船头依旧
And the center of the bow
撞向航标杆的正中间
is still hitting the center of the pole.
只有一点不同
There's only one difference.
劈船为二
是的  造成不同的原因
Yep, and the reason for that difference
流言终结者们应该再熟悉不过了
is very familiar to the mythbusters.
缆绳断了
Cable broke.
在新墨西哥工学院的高科技教室...
And inside NMT's high-tech classroom...
-你好范  -欢迎回来
- Hey, Van. - Welcome back.
范·罗梅罗找到了解决方案
Van Romero has the solution.
让船沿着轨道飞驰不太现实
Flying the boat down a track is a little tricky.
船的时速会达到160  甚至240公里
Getting a boat to go 100, 150 miles an hour --
范·罗梅罗博士
新墨西哥工学院研究副主任
在高速行驶中
What's gonna happen with a fast acceleration
它很有可能散架
is it's probably gonna fly apart.
但我们也有其他选择
But we do have another option.
船可以不动
Instead of moving the boat down the track,
让杆子沿着轨道跑
let's look at moving the piling down the track.
太赞了
Awesome.
如果这样
If we do that,
我们可以达到理想的速度
we can accelerate this pipe as fast as we want.
也不会出现任何问题
We won't have any problems.
物理作用是一致的
The physics is identical,
只要我们尽可能达到
as long as we get the closing speed
想要的速度
to match the closing speed that we want.
角色对换
The roles will be reversed,
航标杆会以快艇的最快速度
and the pylon will hit the boat
撞击快艇
traveling at the top speed of a speedboat.
该去轨道那里
So, it's time to trek back to the track
准备滑道了
and prepare the sled.
你可能会首先注意到  这次的标杆
The first thing you'll probably notice about the pole
和之前实验所用的不同
is unlike our previous experiment,
金属杆代替了木杆
It's metal instead of wood.
因为在高速行驶中
The reason for this is that at the speeds we're talking about,
木杆会粉身碎骨
wood would simply shatter,
而金属杆却不会
where we know the metal's not gonna shatter.
这样才能产生更具作用的动能
The more important kinetic energy is gonna generate.
标杆加上滑板差不多270公斤
The pole plus the sled weighs almost 600 pounds.
它们要以每小时320公里的速度滑行
It's gonna be traveling at nearly 200 miles per hour.
火箭动力滑道实验的关键在于-
See, the key to any good rocket-sled experiment-
润滑
Lubrication.
这样的动能
That's the kind of kinetic energy we need
才有可能劈船为二
to give this boat split a fighting chance.
但首先  需要来点海洋风情的配饰
But first, the marker needs a maritime makeover.
现在我们身处新墨西哥州
So, we're out here in the middle of New Mexico.
周围没啥海  所以...
There's not a lot of ocean around, so...
为了让它更有海洋风情
We decided to make it more marine-like.
我们带来了海鸥
So, we brought a seagull.
还有比这东西听着更让人烦的吗
Is that the most irritating thing you've ever heard?
看标杆美美地站在那...
With the pole sitting pretty...
给船也来点装饰
It's the boat's turn to get nautical.
海浪翻滚
Ocean spray.
我们来给船添点水
We're going to add a little water to this boat
让观众满意
just to keep the fans happy.
观众希望"劈船为二"在水上进行
They really like "Bifurcated boat" to be on water.
随着分裂号3代就位
With the mythity split 3 in commission,
可以杨帆起航了
they hoist the sails.
所以  它飘在空中了
So, it's floating on air.
这种场面可不是每天都能看到的
Well, there's something you don't see every day.
船已经就位
The boat's in place.
可以将火箭装上了
Now it's time to load up the sled with rockets,
看看能不能把船劈成两半
and see if we can split this boat in half.
三  二  一
Three, two, one!
阴险的亚当变通了规则...
Devious Adam moved the goal posts...
电光火石间
Wow, that was quick.
用爆炸创造出艺术作品
And created art with explosives.
漂亮
That's beautiful!
现在该轮到海曼用爆炸粉刷墙面了
But now it's the Hyneman's turn to paint and detonate.
你需要这个
You need that.
没错  开始组装
I do. It's time to load it up.
流言中涂料要达到百分百覆盖
The myth requires 100% wall coverage,
因此杰米减少了炸药用量
so Jamie's reducing his boom.
第一次测试  用的是C4
On our first test, we used C-4,
它是一种高速的烈性炸药
which is a very fast, high explosive.
这次  我们用开沟炸药
This time, we've slowed it down
减速至1/4或者1/5
to about 1/4 or 1/5 of that speed with ditching dynamite.
爆炸速度大概每秒1500米
This stuff goes off at about 5,000 feet per second,
希望它能提供更多的推动力
and I'm hoping that it'll have a lot more push with it.
或许能喷出更多的涂料
Maybe it'll push some paint.
但能让亚当刮目相看吗
But will it impress Adam?
不是吧
No fricking way.
什么  怎么会  它看上去有2700公斤
What- how- this looks like it weighs 6,000 pounds.
只有差不多1600公斤
Oh, it's only 3,500 or so.
天呐
Oh, my god.
这个要怎么运作
How -- how does this work?
就把盖子盖上  拧好螺栓
Well you put the top on, and you bolt it down.
把颜料倒满  炸药一炸
You pour paint in, it fills up, the dynamite goes off,
颜料就从喷口里出来
and it shoots paint out through the jets.
你要是觉得行
If it's okay with you,
我还是到观测室里看吧
I'd like to watch this one from the bunker.
这确实是个危险的玩意
Yeah, this is -- you know, this is a dangerous thing.
也是个漂亮的玩意
It is a beautiful thing.
干得漂亮
Nice work.
炸药摆好之后
And with the dynamite in position,
杰米打算要血染满屋了
Jamie's planning to paint the town red.
谁知道这种特殊喷涂
Who knows what the right paint thickness will be
该调什么浓度的涂料
for this particular spray-paint job.
通常来说
I mean, normally,
喷涂的话用较稀的涂料
you thin paint a little bit when you put it in a sprayer,
所以我觉得没什么差别
so I figure this wouldn't be any different.
不管怎样  浓度越稀
And in any case, the thinner the paint,
喷出后越容易雾化
the more it's gonna break apart when it's sprayed.
索性就弄稀一点以防万一咯
And why not hedge my bet?
涂料填装完毕后
Well, with the paint payload on board,
球形装置准备就绪
the sphere is locked and loaded.
恭喜你
Congratulations.
多年之后  终于造出了死星
After all these years, you finally made the death star.
在它造成任何伤害之前
Well, let's get out of here
我们快撤吧
before it is actually the death star.
一切都准备好了
The circle is now complete.
可以回到基地开火
So it's time to return to base and use the force.
但它可以粉刷整个房间吗
But can it paint an entire room?
好的
Okay.
炸药涂料  涂料球准备
Painting with explosives, the paint ball,
三  二  一  爆炸
in three, two, one, go.
发生了啥
What happened?
-咱们去看看  -好的
- Let's go check it out.  - All right.
和我想象的不太一样
That, uh, wasn't exactly what I had in mind.
但是...
But, um...
你弄出了四幅罗夏测验
You've made a four-wall rorschach test.
利用墨渍图版的人格测验
杰米  看到这些墨点你想到了什么
Jamie, what do you see when you look at this blot?
我想到了情人节
I see Valentine's Day.
情人节吗  它不是-
Valentine's Day? Well, that's not the-
你这人也太浪漫了
Wow. That's quite romantic of you.
谁又知道呢
Who knew?
死星向四周喷出雾化的红涂料
The death ball sprayed a red mist over the walls,
看起来不像粉刷  而是好莱坞的恐怖片
but it looks less solid color and more hollywood horror.
忙了这么久  就这么个结果
All that work, and this is what we get.
这真引人深思  难道不是吗
Well, it's food for thought, isn't it?
虽然没有粉刷整面墙壁
And even though he didn't coat all of the walls,
杰米并不失望
Jamie's not disappointed.
我很高兴我的小球
Well, I'm tickled pink
真的经得起烈性炸药的威力
that my ball actually withstood the high explosive.
这原本是我最担心的事情
That was the main thing that I was worried about.
而染料的确很好地从喷嘴喷出
And the paint actually came out the jets quite nicely.
确实达到了预期
They did what they were supposed to.
喷嘴将喷射的方向指向四周的墙壁
They directed the paint at the walls,
而且你甚至可以观察到喷射器
and you can even see that the jets were starting
将涂料雾喷成了我想要的形状
to shape the spray the way that I wanted to
所以染料没有全部集中在中间
to that it didn't end up all right in the middle.
但至于通过炸药来涂整间房子的话
But as far as painting a house with explosives...
还需下功夫了
it needs a little work.
最后分析
Final analysis,
用炸药涂房子  你怎样看
Painting with explosives -- what do you think?
今天我们干得还不赖
Well, we made some fine art today,
但粉刷房子的话  太不实际了
but as far as painting houses, it's just not practical.
在近期之类它都不会代替房屋油漆工的
No, it's not gonna replace house painters anytime soon.
流言被终结了  我们回家吧
Got to be busted. Let's go home.
其实在一毫秒之内
It would actually be kind of nice
就粉刷好房子挺棒的  不是吗
to be able to paint your house in a millisecond, wouldn't it?
流言终结
休息过后
After the break...
七年的等待过后  我们终于要揭晓
after seven years of waiting to find out
到底可不可以将一艘船一分为二
if we could actually bifurcate a boat,
我们准备好了
we're ready to go.
同时
Meanwhile,
在旧金山某处的画廊里
at a gallery somewhere in san francisco...
我的爆炸画作有什么含义呢
What are my bomb paintings about?
我的意思是  它们代表着
Well, I mean, they're really about
艺术最本质的主题
the universal themes of art,
灵感的爆发
the explosive moment of inspiration,
我们创作的随机性
the randomness of our creation,
在他人的生命中留下的碎屑的痕迹
the marks of detritus we leave on others' lives.
但最主要是因为我喜欢炸东西而已
But mostly it's just 'cause I like to blow up.
新墨西哥州的深处  马上要提速了
Deep in New Mexico, things are about to get fast.
我听说你给我们弄了些火箭
So, I heard you got some rockets for us.
这是我们今天最危险的部分
This is the most dangerous part of our day --
安装火箭
loading the rockets onto the sled.
这的确危险不假
It's dangerous all right.
实际上  因为这太危险了所以需要换装
In fact, it's so dangerous, it requires a costume change.
这是一个非常紧张的时刻
This is an incredibly tense moment,
因为火箭上
and the reason is that the rockets
预先安装了点火器
have their igniters pre-installed.
所以就算只是拿着它们也有可能被点燃
So, just by handling them, they could ignite,
而这真的非常非常糟糕
and that would be a very, very bad thing.
另外一样使得搬运困难的事情是
And the other thing that makes it difficult
火箭被触发的条件并不高
is that the ignition level is not very high,
一伏特加一安培
One volt at one amp.
如果穿着毛线衣在周围走动的话
When you just walk around in wool clothing,
你会产生4万伏特以上
you could generate a static charge
的静电荷
of upwards of 40,000 volts.
这就是为什么我们要拿走任何
So, that's why we have to remove
不是棉布造的东西并且保持与地面接触
anything that's not cotton and ground ourselves
因为我们不想这些火箭发动
Because we don't want these things going off.
没错  他们一直与地面接触
Yep, they're staying grounded
任何火箭的威力
'cause the power of these rockets
可以把他们炸飞
could knock more than their socks off.
为了让塔架以每小时320公里的速度发射
To send this pylon down the track at 200 miles an hour,
我们利用朝鲜战争时
We are using vintage, korean-war,
古老的高速飞机发动机
high-velocity aircraft motors.
这会让我们得到想要的速度
That's gonna give us the 200 miles an hour we need,
375倍的重力加速度  1.2万牛的推力
375 g's, and 12,000 pounds of thrust.
这能让分裂号3代粉身碎骨
It's gonna annihilate the mythity split 3.
的确
Indeed.
塔架会以一艘极速快艇的
That pylon will be traveling
最快速度前进
at the maximum speed a super-fast speedboat can go,
这意味着不能出现错误
which means there's no margin for error.
进入观测室
To the bunker.
我们的高速相机已准备就绪
Okay. So, our high-speed cameras are in place.
我们准备好了
We are ready to go.
见证真相的时候到了
This is the moment of truth.
我觉得什么会发生呢
What do I think is gonna happen?
那是艘玻璃钢船
Look, that's a fiberglass boat.
有根钢杆将要撞上去
It's a steel pole coming at it.
那艘船肯定会粉身碎骨的
That thing is gonna shatter into a million pieces.
记住我的话
Mark my words.
既然有"劈船为二"的诅咒
Well, where the curse of the bifurcated boat is involved,
什么事都不好说
nothing is certain.
他们准备行动了
But they've cleared the decks.
好了  塔架准备好了
All right, the pylon is loaded and hot.
我们的船也就绪了
We've got our boat in place.
做好准备
Batten down the hatches.
这就是了
this is it, man.
但愿我们能将船切成两半
Finally, hopefully, we can cut this boat in half.
只剩全速前进
And now it's full steam ahead.
火箭滑道上的塔架大战小船
All right. Rocket-sled pylon versus boat.
三  二  一
Three, two, one.
一分为二了
Wow! We got bifurcation!
就从中间切开
It cut right down the middle!
我们成功了
We did it finally!
哈哈  太棒了
Ha-ha! Awesome!
这真棒
That was awesome.
没错  似乎诅咒解除了
Yep, it seems the curse has lifted,
他们终于将船一分为二
and they finally split the boat.
过了那么久  我们终于把船劈成两半了
Finally! After all this time, we bifurcated a boat.
你知道这代表什么吗
But you know what that shows me?
一定要快才行
That dude had to be going fast.
-非常快  -没错
- Real fast. - Yep.
我们去看看现场怎样
Let's go check out the carnage.
好的
All right.
在外面  很明显船已经毁了
Outside, it's clear that this ship is wrecked.
我不能告诉你这船终于被分开后
I cannot tell you how happy I am
我有多开心
that this boat is finally split.
它被分成两块了
It split in two.
虽然船被毁了  但是很明显被分开了
I mean, it's annihilated, but there is a clear division.
火箭滑道不会让人失望的
The rocket sled does not disappoint.
的确
It does not.
在短短60米内加速到每小时320公里
Reaching 200 miles per hour in only 200 feet,
塔架冲进了船头
the rocket-powered pylon plowed into the prow,
将船抛向空中
tossing the boat into the air
只留下船的两半
and leaving two halves in its wake.
好的  所以我的预测是
All right, so, my prediction
当航标杆撞击小船后
was that when the channel marker hit the boat,
小船会粉身碎骨
it would shatter into a million pieces.
可如你所见  它几乎在船体上
But as you can see here, it actually tore a hole
撕开了一个裂口
almost all the way down the hull,
留给我们两个几乎完整的部分
leaving this in two pretty-much-intact halves.
我从未如此高兴地说我错了
I've never been happier to say that I was wrong.
这意味着如果速度足够快
And it just goes to show
即使一个钝如航标杆的物体
that even a blunt object like our channel marker
也能变成一把利器
could turn into a knife when you add enough speed.
那人不可能以每小时40公里的速度行驶
There's no way that guy was going 25 miles an hour.
时速40公里我们试了许多次
We tried it over and over at 25.
陆地  水上都试过
We tried it off water, on water.
到了每小时320公里的速度我们才成功
It took 200 before it started to split it.
每小时40公里简直毫发无损
We didn't even get a dent at 25.
我觉得他可能说谎了
I think he might have been lying.
历时七年
Seven years in the making,
四个航标杆  三艘小船
four channel markers, three boats,
一艘驳船  一辆吊车
a barge, and a crane,
没有一样东西能将小船一分为二
but nothing could bifurcate the boat
直到现在
until now.
并借助火箭滑道
With a rocket powered sled.
但这个流言还是被终结了
But it looks like this one is still busted.
真有意思啊
That was fun.
接下来还能把啥放到火箭滑道上
What do you think we can put on the rocket sled next.
不知
I don't know.
我们中的一个咋样
Any of us.
流言终结